<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/"
  article-type="#article_type#" dtd-version="1.1">
  <front>

    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">#journal_title#</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">#journal_title#</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">#journal_title#</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>#journal_title#</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">#journal_issn#</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>iMaQPress</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Tbilisi, Georgia</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>

    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">#publish_number#</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">#doi#</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="categories">
          #keywords#
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>#article_full_title#</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group content-type="authors">
        #authors#
        #author_affs#
      </contrib-group>

      <contrib-group content-type="editors">
        #editors#
      </contrib-group>

      <volume>#article_publish_vol#</volume>
      <elocation-id>#article_id#</elocation-id>

      <history>
        <date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="#article_created_at#">
          <day>#article_created_at_day#</day>
          <month>#article_created_at_month#</month>
          <year iso-8601-date="#article_created_at_year#">#article_created_at_year#</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="#article_publish_date#">
          <day>#article_publish_date_day#</day>
          <month>#article_publish_date_month#</month>
          <year iso-8601-date="#article_publish_date_year#">#article_publish_date_year#</year>
        </date>
      </history>

      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>
        © #article_publish_date_year# #authors_head#
        </copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>#article_publish_date_year#</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>#authors_head#</copyright-holder>
        <license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
          <license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
              xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution
              License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any
            medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s),
            title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>

      <self-url xlink:href="#article_publish_link#" />

      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Abstract</title>
          <p>Full abstract of article</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>

      <kwd-group kwd-group-type="Keywords">
        <kwd>Abstract Keyword 1</kwd>
        <kwd>Abstract Keyword 2</kwd>
        <kwd>Abstract Keyword 3</kwd>
        <kwd>Abstract Keyword 4</kwd>
        <kwd>Abstract Keyword 5</kwd>
      </kwd-group>

      <funding-group>
        <funding-statement> Acknowledgement Statement.</funding-statement>
      </funding-group>

    </article-meta>

  </front>

  <head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8">
    <meta name="description" content="One sentence summary should come here">
    <meta name="focus keyword" content="running title should come here">
    <meta name="editor" content="Chief Editor name of journal should come here">
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0">
  </head>

  <body>

    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is one of the most common malignancies in the world (<xref ref-type="bibr"
          rid="ref-23">Omata et al., 2017</xref>). In 1996, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-21">Mazzaferro et al. (1996)
        </xref> reported that liver transplantation (LT) was considered an optimal radical therapy for selected patients
        with HCC. By removing HCC tumors with the greatest possible margin and replacing cirrhotic liver tissue with a
        tumor-free graft, LT has a better curative effect for liver cancer than hepatectomy (<xref ref-type="bibr"
          rid="ref-17">Lee et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
      <p>However, a significant proportion of HCC patients who undergo LT still suffer from unfavorable outcomes due to
        the chance of tumor recurrence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-26">Trojan, Zangos &amp; Schnitzbauer, 2016
        </xref>). One reason for the poor prognosis of liver cancer is that cancer cells can easily enter and spread
        through the bloodstream. Before surgical resection, these circulating tumor cells (CTCs) may be present in the
        patient’s blood. Surgical operations also carry the risk of causing CTCs to enter the bloodstream (<xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2">Alix-Panabières &amp; Pantel, 2014</xref>). Thus, CTCs are currently a major focus
        of liver cancer research because of the key roles they play in HCC recurrence and metastasis (<xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-20">Masuda et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-16">Kelley et al.,
          2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3">Choi et al., 2015</xref>).</p>
      <p>Several strategies have been used to separate blood for the analysis of CTCs. The most common enrichment
        approach, called immunoaffinity enrichment technology, such as applied by the CellSearch system, uses antibodies
        targeting epithelial cell adhesion molecule (EpCAM). This system is the only CTC isolation method currently
        approved by the US Food and Drug Administration for prognostic use. More recently, a number of approaches have
        been proposed for the isolation of CTCs using immunoaffinity selection, such as the CTC-chip (<xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-22">Nagrath et al., 2007</xref>), GEDI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-9">Galletti et
          al., 2014</xref>), GEM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-25">Sheng et al., 2014</xref>), and Abnova CytoQuest™
        CR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-29">Zhao et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-12">Hou et al.,
          2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-27">Wang et al., 2011</xref>), which still use EpCAM and other
        surface antigens as target moieties. However, CTCs may also undergo changes during disease states, such as
        epithelial–mesenchymal transition (EMT), accompanied by changes in CTC surface markers, leading to mesenchymal
        tumor cells with an increased stem-like phenotype and reduced epithelial phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr"
          rid="ref-10">Giannelli et al., 2016</xref>). This may be why CTC detection rates and counts achieved using
        this enrichment technology are generally low and the entire population of CTCs cannot be collected (<xref
          ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-5">De Boer et al., 1999</xref>).</p>
      <p>In this research, we attempted to combine emerging microfluidic technologies with magnetic-based cell sorting
        to generate a miniaturized, low-cost and antigen-independent tool for efficient CTC separation (<xref
          ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Figs. 1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">1B</xref>). Microfluidics,
        which integrates physical, chemical, and biological technologies at the microscale level, has been used to
        create devices known as labs-on-a-chip or micro total analysis systems. A new type of microfluidic structure
        using deterministic lateral displacement (DLD) was designed for the continuous high-throughput separating of
        whole blood from HCC patients to isolate nucleated cells, including CTCs and white blood cells (WBCs),
        efficiently with minimal damage and independent of antigens. Then, StraightFrom® Whole Blood CD45 MicroBeads and
        a magnetic-activated cell sorting (MACS) separator are used to remove bead-labeled WBCs from the DLD structure
        and ultimately concentrate unlabeled CTCs.</p>
      <fig id="fig-1">
        <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6681/fig-1</object-id>
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Platform schematic and structural design.</title>
          <p>(A) This capture platform integrates a DLD structure with a MACS separator for inline operation. Step 1:
            The DLD removes nucleated cells from whole blood by size-based deflection using a specially designed array
            of microposts. Step 2: The MACS separator serves to sensitively separate bead-labeled WBCs and unlabeled
            CTCs. (B) The overall system integrates syringe pumps, the DLD chip and the MACS separator into an operating
            platform. Before the sample enters the chip, a micro-oscillator mixes the blood to avoid stratification of
            the blood in the tube. (C) DLD device design. (i) Two inlets inject blood and buffer separately, the filter
            array ensures that blood flows along a certain direction; (ii) The device consists of two mirrored arrays of
            egg-shaped microposts with a pillar size and array offset designed to deflect particles larger than a
            certain size, thereby separating them from the main suspension; (iii) Two outlets are designed for the
            deflected product and undeflected waste. Photo credit: Xuebin Wang.</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6681/fig-1.png" />
      </fig>
      <p>We also compared our platform with the Abnova CytoQuest™ CR system (Taipei, Taiwan) in separating and
        characterizing CTCs from HCC patients undergoing LT and performed follow-up analyses of HCC patients with early
        postoperative metastases. As CTCs from these samples underwent EMT, the detection sensitivity of the Abnova
        CytoQuest™ CR system was reduced, whereas our capture platform was not affected and yielded high CTC counts.</p>
      <p>The results demonstrate that our capture platform is highly efficient independent from antigens and is thus
        clinically valuable.</p>
    </sec>

    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Deterministic lateral displacement microfluidic device design and function</title>
        <p>The overall microfluidic DLD isolation platform is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1C</xref>.
          This device is a size-based continuous-flow system because CTCs are generally larger in size than other blood
          cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-11">Harouaka, Nisic &amp; Zheng, 2013</xref>). The system consists of an
          array of microposts with a pillar size and array offset designed to deflect particles above a certain size,
          thereby separating them from the main suspension (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-15">Karabacak et al., 2014
          </xref>). The design is based on the DLD theory proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-13">Huang et al.
            (2004)</xref>.</p>
        <p>The flow chamber is 33 mm long, two mm wide, and 30 µm high. The microarray consists of two mirrored arrays
          of egg-shaped microposts, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1C</xref>, with the arrays at an
          angle of 1.7 ° with respect to the fluid flow direction. Based on the theoretical principle of DLD (<xref
            ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-14">Inglis et al., 2006</xref>), the critical particle diameter is approximately
          four to five µm. With this design, most of the red blood cells (RBCs) and platelets (PLTs) pass through the
          gaps and are removed through the outlet, while CTCs and some leukocytes are collected once they are
          concentrated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Deterministic lateral displacement microfluidic device fabrication</title>
        <p>Microfluidic devices were fabricated using standard photolithography and soft lithography (<xref
            ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-7">Faustino et al., 2016</xref>). The negative photoresist SU-8 3025 (MicroChem,
          Naton, MA, USA) was used to fabricate the master on a silicon wafer with a photomask. Next,
          polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS) prepolymer mixed with a curing agent (8:1 w/w ratio) was poured onto the silicon
          wafer and baked at 80 °C for 1 h; subsequently, holes were punched for the inlet and outlets. Finally, the
          PDMS microfluidic channels and glass substrate were exposed to oxygen plasma (PDC-M; Chengdu Mingheng Science
          &amp; Technology Co., Ltd., P. R. China) for 1 min and then brought into contact to bond together. The devices
          were left overnight in a 65 °C oven to complete the irreversible bonding process between the PDMS and glass.
        </p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Magnetic-activated cell sorting separator and preparation</title>
        <p>We used StraightFrom Whole Blood CD45 MicroBeads and a MACS separator (Miltenyi Biotec, Bergisch Gladbach,
          Germany) developed for the rapid selection of CD45<sup>+</sup> cells directly from whole peripheral blood to
          remove bead-labeled WBCs and concentrate unlabeled CTCs. Unlike standard magnetic beads, Whole Blood CD45
          MicroBeads have the advantage of not requiring sample preparation, such as density gradient centrifugation or
          erythrocyte lysis. MicroBeads (50 µl) were added to every one ml of anticoagulated whole blood. The samples
          were mixed well and incubated for 15 min in a refrigerator (2–8 °C).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Platform module integration</title>
        <p>The overall system is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1B</xref>. The platform is driven by
          four syringe pumps. Two of the pumps are loaded with a 50-ml syringe containing 40 ml of prepared blood
          suspensions, and the remaining two pumps are loaded with a 50-ml syringe containing 50 ml of
          phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). Teflon tubes (one mm) connect the syringe pumps to the microfluidic device,
          and two small vibrators are located in front of the inlets. Some leukocytes and most cancer cells are
          deflected to the product outlet once they are concentrated, while the remaining blood, which is diluted with
          buffer, is collected via waste tubing. Collected cells drop down from the product outlet of the DLD device,
          which contains highly bead-labeled WBCs and CTCs, and enter the MACS column. Then, magnetically labeled
          CD45<sup>+</sup> WBCs are retained within the column, while unlabeled cells (mostly CTCs) pass through the
          column and are collected at the final product outlet.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Hepatocellular carcinoma cells</title>
        <p>To characterize the efficacy of the DLD device, we established HepG2 human liver cancer cells overexpressing
          green fluorescent protein (GFP) by lentiviral transfection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2A</xref>),
          allowing the observation of these cells using a fluorescence microscope. Cells were cultured in low-glucose
          Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum and 1% penicillin-streptomycin at
          37 °C with 5% (v/v) CO<sub>2</sub>. The culture medium was changed every 2 days. Cells were harvested by
          incubation in 0.05% trypsin with 0.53 mM ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) at 37 °C for 3 min and were
          then diluted to the desired concentration.</p>
        <fig id="fig-2">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6681/fig-2</object-id>
          <label>Figure 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>HepG2-GFP cells and isolation efficiency ratio with different flow rates.</title>
            <p>(A) Modeling the presence of cancer cells in human peripheral blood using HepG2-GFP cells. (B) Isolation
              efficiency ratio for different flow rates. A specimen flow rate of 60 μl/min and a buffer flow rate of 100
              μl/min yielded an isolation efficiency ratio of 85.1 ± 3.2%.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6681/fig-2.png" />
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Blood samples and follow-up</title>
        <p>Fresh whole blood samples were collected from 10 healthy volunteers and 12 HCC patients undergoing LT (<xref
            ref-type="table" rid="table-1">Table 1</xref>) in the Transplant Section of the Beijing Friendship Hospital
          in China between September 2017 and May 2018. Blood was obtained prior to transplantation for HCC patients
          (baseline) and then at follow-up visits 1 and 3 months after the surgery. Recurrence was diagnosed based on
          typical imaging findings on computed tomography (CT), magnetic resonance imaging or bone scans. At each time
          point, 7.5 ml of fresh whole blood was collected into EDTA-containing tubes from each subject for analysis by
          our DLD platform and the CytoQuest™ CR system within 6 h. Clinical information was also collected, including
          the alpha-fetoprotein level, size, and number of tumors, Milan criteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-21">
            Mazzaferro et al., 1996</xref>), presence of hepatitis virus and vascular invasion.</p>
        <table-wrap id="table-1">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6681/table-1</object-id>
          <label>Table 1</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Patient characteristics.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6681/table-1.png" />
            <table content-type="text">
              <colgroup>
                <col />
                <col />
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th>Variables</th>
                  <th>Liver transplantation (<italic>n</italic> = 12) (%)</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2">Sex</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Male</td>
                  <td>8(66.7)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Female</td>
                  <td>4(33.3)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2">Age, years</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> ≤50</td>
                  <td>7(58.3)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> &gt;50</td>
                  <td>5(41.7)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2">Etiology</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Hepatitis B</td>
                  <td>9(75)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Other</td>
                  <td>3(25)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2">Tumor number</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Single</td>
                  <td>5(41.7)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Multiple</td>
                  <td>7(58.3)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2">Tumor size, cm</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> ≤5</td>
                  <td>3(25)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> &gt;50</td>
                  <td>9(75)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2">Vascular invasion</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> No</td>
                  <td>6(50)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Yes</td>
                  <td>6(50)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2">Milan criteria</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Within</td>
                  <td>4(33.3)</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Beyond</td>
                  <td>8(66.7)</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Written informed consent was obtained from all patients. Approval from the Beijing Friendship Hospital Human
          Research Ethics Committee (code: 2018-P2-114-01) was obtained for the use of all samples using a protocol that
          conforms to the provisions of the Declaration of Helsinki.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Isolation efficiency of the platform integrating DLD with MACS separation</title>
        <p>To determine the best flow rates and obtain the best isolation efficiency ratio from the device, we spiked a
          small number of HepG2-GFP cells into blood samples to model the presence of cancer cells in human peripheral
          blood. Blood samples provided by healthy volunteers were collected into EDTA-containing tubes and diluted 10
          times with PBS to prevent channel blocking. HepG2-GFP cells were then spiked into the diluted blood specimens
          at 1 × 10<sup>2</sup> cells/ml.</p>
        <p>The sample and buffer were injected into the specimen and buffer inlets, respectively, at different flow
          rates, following the principle that the sample liquid level and the buffer liquid level would meet at the
          center of the chip. We counted the HepG2-GFP cells using a fluorescence microscope to select the best flow
          rates, and we then obtained the isolation efficiency ratio, <italic>R</italic>, using the equation
          <inline-formula>
            <alternatives>
              <inline-graphic xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6681/ieqn-1.png" />
              <tex-math id="tex-ieqn-1">
                <![CDATA[$R = {C_1}{V_1}/\left( {{C_1}{V_1} + {C_2}{V_2}} \right)$]]>
              </tex-math>
              <mml:math id="mml-ieqn-1">
                <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:msub>
                  <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                  <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                </mml:msub>
                <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                    </mml:msub>
                    <mml:msub>
                      <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                      <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                    </mml:msub>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </alternatives>
          </inline-formula>, where <italic>C</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub>1</sub> denote the
          concentration and solution volume of the final product outlet, respectively, while <italic>C</italic>
          <sub>2</sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub>2</sub> denote the respective concentration and solution volume of the
          waste outlet. The experiment was repeated 10 times.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>HepG2-GFP cell sorting experiments</title>
        <p>To examine whether there were differences in the enrichment effects of different concentrations of HCC cells,
          we spiked HepG2-GFP cells into 10-fold diluted whole blood at 50, 1 × 10<sup>2</sup>, 2 × 10<sup>2</sup>, 4 ×
          10<sup>2</sup>, and 8 × 10<sup>2</sup> cells/ml. At the best flow rates, we recalculated the isolation
          efficiency as described above. Each concentration was tested 10 times.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Debulking efficiency</title>
        <p>To characterize the performance of the platform in removing blood cells (mainly RBCs, PLTs, WBCs), we spiked
          HepG2-GFP cells into 10-fold diluted whole blood at 1 × 10<sup>2</sup> cells/ml and injected them into the
          device under the best flow rates. After the device was running stably, we calculated the removal ratio
          <italic>R<sub>r</sub></italic> using the equation <inline-formula>
            <alternatives>
              <inline-graphic xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6681/ieqn-2.png" />
              <tex-math id="tex-ieqn-2">
                <![CDATA[${R_r} = \left( {{C_2}{V_2} - {C_1}{V_1}} \right)/{C_2}{V_2}$]]>
              </tex-math>
              <mml:math id="mml-ieqn-2">
                <mml:mrow>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                  <mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                    <mml:mrow>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                      <mml:msub>
                        <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                      </mml:msub>
                    </mml:mrow>
                    <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                  </mml:mrow>
                  <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                  </mml:msub>
                  <mml:msub>
                    <mml:mi>V</mml:mi>
                    <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                  </mml:msub>
                </mml:mrow>
              </mml:math>
            </alternatives>
          </inline-formula>, where <italic>C</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub>1</sub> denote the
          concentration and solution volume of the final product outlet, respectively, while <italic>C</italic>
          <sub>2</sub> and <italic>V</italic><sub>2</sub> denote the respective concentration and solution volume of the
          starting sample. A hemocytometer was used to count blood cells, and the experiment was repeated 10 times.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Abnova CytoQuest™ CR system</title>
        <p>The CytoQuest™ CR system is a rare cell sorting system developed by Abnova and the UCLA (University of
          California Los Angeles) Nano Research Institute. The system is a modified NanoVelcro Chip that is capable of
          efficiently capturing CTCs in patient blood samples using anti-EpCAM-coated silicon nanowire substrates.
          Circulating tumor cell enumeration by CytoQuest™ CR was carried out according to the manufacturer’s protocol (
          <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-27">Wang et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-29">Zhao et al.,
            2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-12">Hou et al., 2013</xref>). First, 7.5 ml of blood was drawn
          into an EDTA-containing collection tube. Next, the buffy coat containing CTCs was separated by gradient cell
          separation. After washing with PBS, the prepared buffy coat was injected into an EpCAM-coated microfluidic
          slide to capture CTCs.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Immunostaining and identification of captured cells</title>
        <p>Circulating tumor cells were identified and counted manually. After the produced sample was transferred to a
          50-ml centrifuge tube and centrifuged at 600<italic>×g</italic> for 5 min, the supernatant was aspirated.
          Then, the cell pellet was diluted to five ml by PBS and divided equally on 10 glass slides (Thermo Fisher
          Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA).</p>
        <p>Cells on the glass slides were fixed with 4% formaldehyde for 15 min at room temperature and then
          permeabilized with 0.1% Triton X-100 in PBS. To identify CTCs, double immunofluorescence staining was
          performed with anti-cytokeratin-fluorescein isothiocyanate (anti-CK-FITC; Miltenyi Biotec, Bergisch Gladbach,
          Germany) and anti-CD45- allophycocyanin (anti-CD45-APC; Miltenyi Biotec, Bergisch Gladbach, Germany).
          4′,6-Diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI; Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) was used to stain nuclei. To identify
          CTCs undergoing EMT, cells were stained with anti-vimentin- phycoerythrin (anti-vimentin-PE; Miltenyi Biotec,
          Bergisch Gladbach, Germany). Cells were counted using confocal laser scanning microscopy (Lecia, Wetzlar,
          Germany).</p>
        <p>The criteria for WBCs were as follows: round/ovoid, DAPI<sup>+</sup>/CD45<sup>+</sup>/CK<sup>−</sup> cells ≤6
          µm in size. Circulating tumor cells were defined as round/ovoid
          DAPI<sup>+</sup>/CD45<sup>−</sup>/CK<sup>+</sup> cells ≥6 µm in size. Circulating tumor cells undergoing EMT
          were defined as round/ovoid, DAPI<sup>+</sup>/CD45<sup>−</sup>/CK<sup>+</sup>/vimentin<sup>+</sup> cells ≥6 µm
          in size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-4">Court et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-28">Yu et
            al., 2016</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>All statistical analyses were performed using SPSS (version 22.0; IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA). Variance
          analysis was used to examine whether the isolation efficiency varied with cell concentration. A pairwise
          comparison between CTCs counted at different time points after detection by our integrated DLD platform and
          the CytoQuest™ CR system was performed by applying the nonparametric Wilcoxon signed-rank test. Graphical
          plots were generated using GraphPad Prism 6.0 (GraphPad Software, La Jolla, CA, USA). All <italic>P</italic>
          -values were two-sided, and <italic>P-</italic>values of less than 0.05 were considered statistically
          significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Isolation efficiency and optimal flow rates for the platform integrating DLD with MACS separation</title>
        <p>HepG2-GFP cells were spiked into 10-fold diluted whole blood at a concentration of 1 × 10<sup>2</sup>
          cells/ml. At different sample flow rates of 20, 60, 120, 200, 300, 500, 800, and 1,200 μl/min, buffer was
          injected into the device at flow rates of 30, 100, 170, 280, 400, 630, 950, and 1,500 μl/min. The
          corresponding isolation efficiency ratios were 86.4% ± 3.7% (mean ± SD), 85.1% ± 3.2%, 73.7% ± 3.5%, 69.0% ±
          3.3%, 62.5% ± 3.8%, 52.2% ± 3.5%, 24.3% ± 3.9%, and 12.6% ± 3.2%, respectively.</p>
        <p>The cell isolation efficiency decreased significantly with increasing flow rate. To maintain a balance
          between isolation efficiency and time, we selected a specimen flow rate of 60 μl/min and a buffer flow rate of
          100 μl/min, which yielded an isolation efficiency ratio of approximately 85.1% ± 3.2%, as shown in <xref
            ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2B</xref>.</p>
        <p>The flow of blood in the chip observed continuously through an optical microscope, as shown in <xref
            ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3A</xref>.</p>
        <fig id="fig-3">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6681/fig-3</object-id>
          <label>Figure 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>DLD platform enrichment experiment using blood samples.</title>
            <p>(A) The flow of blood in the chip observed through an optical microscope. Small cells, mainly composed of
              RBCs, flowed in a straight line, while large cells flowed at an angle and separated from the main
              suspension. (B) Samples obtained at different stages. Almost all RBCs were removed by the DLD chip. Photo
              credit: Xuebin Wang.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6681/fig-3.png" />
        </fig>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Isolation efficiency with different concentrations of cultured HCC cells</title>
        <p>We spiked HepG2-GFP cells into 10-fold diluted whole blood at 50, 1 × 10<sup>2</sup>, 2 × 10<sup>2</sup>, 4 ×
          10<sup>2</sup>, and 8 × 10<sup>2</sup> cells/ml. At a specimen flow rate of 60 μl/min and a buffer flow rate
          of 100 μl/min, the isolation efficiency ratio was 85.2% ± 3.6%, 85.6% ± 3.3%, 84.8% ± 3.3%, 85.0% ± 3.1%, and
          85.1% ± 3.5%, respectively. Analysis of variance suggested no significant differences between the different
          groups (<italic>P</italic> = 0.972 &gt; 0.05).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Debulking efficiency and enrichment performance</title>
        <p>The calculated results show that the RBC, WBC, and PLT removal rates were 99.90% ± 0.03%, 98.50% ± 0.13%, and
          99.95% ± 0.05%, respectively. Significant changes in the appearance of the samples as shown in <xref
            ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3B</xref>. HepG2-GFP cells had 852 × enrichment over RBCs, 57 × enrichment
          over WBCs and 1,715 × enrichment over PLTs as illustrated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table-2">Table 2
          </xref>.</p>
        <table-wrap id="table-2">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6681/table-2</object-id>
          <label>Table 2</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Relative concentrations of erythrocytes, leukocytes, platelets, and HepG2-GFP recovered from the
              collected solution at a specimen flow rate of 60 μl/min and a buffer flow rate of 100 μl/min.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6681/table-2.png" />
            <table content-type="text">
              <colgroup>
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th rowspan="2" />
                  <th colspan="4">Concentration (%)</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th>Erythrocytes</th>
                  <th>Leukocytes</th>
                  <th>Platelets</th>
                  <th>HepG2-GFP</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td>Sample</td>
                  <td>100</td>
                  <td>100</td>
                  <td>100</td>
                  <td>100</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Collected solution</td>
                  <td>0.100 ± 0.015</td>
                  <td>1.500 ± 0.017</td>
                  <td>0.050 ± 0.003</td>
                  <td>85.100 ± 3.213</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Patient characteristics and follow-up</title>
        <p>Among the 12 enrolled patients with HCC, 7/12 (58.3%) had multiple tumors, 9/12 (75%) had a tumor size
          greater than five cm, 8/12 (66.7%) extended the Milan criteria, and 6/12 (50%) had vascular invasion.
          Hepatocellular carcinoma recurrence after LT was observed in two patients (16.7%) during follow-up. One
          example of metastasis is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4A</xref>. The patient was a
          65-year-old male with diagnoses of hepatitis B cirrhosis and HCC. He underwent LT, which revealed a 20-cm
          dominant lesion with multiple satellite lesions and microvascular invasion. However, he was found to have
          multifocal lung nodules on his 3-month follow-up CT scan and then died from respiratory failure. Another
          example of metastasis is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4B</xref>. The patient was a
          49-year-old male with a history of hepatitis B cirrhosis and HCC who had undergone radical hepatectomy 1 year
          prior. Due to the recurrence of HCC, he underwent LT, which revealed a three-cm dominant lesion. At 2 months
          after LT, bone scans indicated bone metastasis.</p>
        <fig id="fig-4">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6681/fig-4</object-id>
          <label>Figure 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Preoperative CT and MRI scans, intraoperative tumor images and evidence of postoperative metastasis
              for two patients with tumor metastases.</title>
            <p>(A), (B), and (C) showed HCC patient no. 1. (A) Axial portal venous phase CT showed multiple, ill-defined
              lesions in liver (red line). The multiple lesions were presented hypodense, relative to the surrounding
              liver, in portal venous phase; (B) HCC nodules removed during surgery (white line); (C) Axial chest CT
              showed multiple, ill-defined, oval nodules in lungs (red line). The nodules were distributed at random.
              Combined with the clinical history, the lesions were considered as metastasis. (D), (E), and (F) showed
              HCC patient no. 2. (D) Axial arterial phase TIWI C<sup>+</sup> showed well-defined, focal lesion in liver
              (arrow). The lesion was presented heterogeneous hypointense enhancement in later arterial phase; (E) HCC
              nodules removed during surgery (arrow); (F) Bone scans showed a focal lesion with hypermetabolism in right
              femoral cavity (arrow). There was no obvious bone destruction around the lesion. Based on the clinical
              history, the lesion was considered as metastasis. Photo credit: Xuebin Wang.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6681/fig-4.png" />
        </fig>
        <p>Ten healthy volunteers were followed for an equivalent amount of time. None of the healthy control patients
          involved in the study developed HCC during follow-up.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Follow-up detection of CTCs using our DLD platform and the CytoQuest™ CR system</title>
        <p>We tested the clinical feasibility of using our device to isolate CTCs from preoperative HCC patients and
          healthy volunteers. We successfully collected CTCs from all HCC patients (100%), while a single CTC was found
          in 2/10 (20%) healthy control volunteers, representing a false positive.</p>
        <p>The number of CTCs detected in patients by our integrated platform and the CytoQuest™ CR system is shown in
          <xref ref-type="table" rid="table-3">Table 3</xref>. Among patients with no metastasis, no significant
          differences in the CTC detection results were found at the three-time points by the Wilcoxon signed-rank test
          (preoperation: <italic>P</italic> = 0.472 &gt; 0.05; 1 month postoperation: <italic>P</italic> = 0.145 &gt;
          0.05; 3 months postoperation: <italic>P</italic> = 0.395 &gt; 0.05). However, among patients with metastasis,
          significantly different CTC counts were detected by our DLD platform and the CytoQuest™ CR system.</p>
        <table-wrap id="table-3">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6681/table-3</object-id>
          <label>Table 3</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The number of CTCs in every 7.5 ml of whole blood from patients detected by the DLD integrated
              platform and CytoQuest™ CR system.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6681/table-3.png" />
            <table content-type="text">
              <colgroup>
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th rowspan="2">No. of patients</th>
                  <th colspan="10">No metastasis</th>
                  <th colspan="2">Metastasis</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th>1</th>
                  <th>2</th>
                  <th>3</th>
                  <th>4</th>
                  <th>5</th>
                  <th>6</th>
                  <th>7</th>
                  <th>8</th>
                  <th>9</th>
                  <th>10</th>
                  <th>1</th>
                  <th>2</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="13">Preoperation</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> DLD platform
                    <break />CTC counts</td>
                  <td>30</td>
                  <td>11</td>
                  <td>9</td>
                  <td>12</td>
                  <td>28</td>
                  <td>14</td>
                  <td>22</td>
                  <td>26</td>
                  <td>10</td>
                  <td>36</td>
                  <td>35</td>
                  <td>25</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> CytoQuest™ CR
                    <break />CTC counts</td>
                  <td>36</td>
                  <td>9</td>
                  <td>4</td>
                  <td>13</td>
                  <td>25</td>
                  <td>16</td>
                  <td>20</td>
                  <td>25</td>
                  <td>7</td>
                  <td>38</td>
                  <td>1</td>
                  <td>5</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="13">1 month postoperation</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> DLD platform
                    <break />CTC counts</td>
                  <td>7</td>
                  <td>4</td>
                  <td>5</td>
                  <td>9</td>
                  <td>7</td>
                  <td>3</td>
                  <td>11</td>
                  <td>10</td>
                  <td>4</td>
                  <td>10</td>
                  <td>15</td>
                  <td>10</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> CytoQuest™ CR
                    <break />CTC counts</td>
                  <td>5</td>
                  <td>1</td>
                  <td>2</td>
                  <td>6</td>
                  <td>5</td>
                  <td>5</td>
                  <td>12</td>
                  <td>13</td>
                  <td>2</td>
                  <td>8</td>
                  <td>5</td>
                  <td>6</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="13">3 months postoperation</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> DLD platform
                    <break />CTC counts</td>
                  <td>40</td>
                  <td>5</td>
                  <td>3</td>
                  <td>11</td>
                  <td>10</td>
                  <td>7</td>
                  <td>12</td>
                  <td>9</td>
                  <td>6</td>
                  <td>5</td>
                  <td>30</td>
                  <td>20</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> CytoQuest™ CR
                    <break />CTC counts</td>
                  <td>34</td>
                  <td>5</td>
                  <td>2</td>
                  <td>9</td>
                  <td>11</td>
                  <td>4</td>
                  <td>20</td>
                  <td>9</td>
                  <td>6</td>
                  <td>4</td>
                  <td>19</td>
                  <td>15</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
        <p>Examination of the two metastatic patients using the CytoQuest™ CR system before and after LT revealed
          relatively low numbers of CTCs (preoperation: 1 and 5; 1 month postoperation: 5 and 6; 3 months postoperation:
          19 and 15), whereas our DLD integrated platform collected significantly more cells (preoperation: 35 and 25; 1
          month postoperation: 15 and 10; 3 months postoperation: 30 and 20).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Detection of vimentin<sup>+</sup> CTCs</title>
        <p>We further analyzed the CTCs extracted by our DLD integrated platform and the CytoQuest™ CR system before
          surgery by examining the expression of vimentin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Fig. 5</xref>), an EMT
          marker (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-24">Satelli &amp; Li, 2011</xref>). As shown in <xref ref-type="table"
            rid="table-4">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Fig. 6</xref>, immunostaining showed that
          vimentin<sup>+</sup> CTCs were found in 4/10 (40%) and 2/10 (20%) patients without metastasis by our DLD
          integrated platform and the CytoQuest™ CR system, respectively, and the counts were low.</p>
        <fig id="fig-5">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6681/fig-5</object-id>
          <label>Figure 5</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Fluorescence images of CTCs and WBCs.</title>
            <p>Immunofluorescence images of cells stained with antibodies against CK (green, CTC marker), CD45 (red,
              leukocyte marker), and DAPI (nuclear stain, blue). Anti-vimentin antibody (orange) was used to identify
              CTCs undergoing EMT.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6681/fig-5.png" />
        </fig>
        <fig id="fig-6">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6681/fig-6</object-id>
          <label>Figure 6</label>
          <caption>
            <title>Numbers of CTCs that were enriched by the DLD integrated platform and CytoQuest™ CR system in HCC
              patients before surgery, including different subpopulations of vimentin<sup>+</sup> and vimentin-cells.
            </title>
            <p>(A) Numbers of CTCs that were enriched by CytoQuest™ CR system. (B) Numbers of CTCs that were enriched by
              the DLD integrated platform.</p>
          </caption>
          <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6681/fig-6.png" />
        </fig>
        <table-wrap id="table-4">
          <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6681/table-4</object-id>
          <label>Table 4</label>
          <caption>
            <title>The number of vimentin<sup>−</sup> and vimentin<sup>+</sup> CTCs in every 7.5 ml of whole blood from
              patients before surgery detected by the DLD integrated platform and CytoQuest™ CR system.</title>
          </caption>
          <alternatives>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6681/table-4.png" />
            <table content-type="text">
              <colgroup>
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
                <col />
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th rowspan="2">No. of patients</th>
                  <th colspan="10">No metastasis</th>
                  <th colspan="2">Metastasis</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th>1</th>
                  <th>2</th>
                  <th>3</th>
                  <th>4</th>
                  <th>5</th>
                  <th>6</th>
                  <th>7</th>
                  <th>8</th>
                  <th>9</th>
                  <th>10</th>
                  <th>1</th>
                  <th>2</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="13">DLD platform</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Vimentin<sup>−</sup> CTCs</td>
                  <td>27</td>
                  <td>11</td>
                  <td>9</td>
                  <td>9</td>
                  <td>28</td>
                  <td>14</td>
                  <td>20</td>
                  <td>25</td>
                  <td>10</td>
                  <td>36</td>
                  <td>7</td>
                  <td>12</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Vimentin<sup>+</sup> CTCs</td>
                  <td>3</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>3</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>1</td>
                  <td>1</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>28</td>
                  <td>13</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Total</td>
                  <td>30</td>
                  <td>11</td>
                  <td>9</td>
                  <td>12</td>
                  <td>28</td>
                  <td>14</td>
                  <td>21</td>
                  <td>26</td>
                  <td>10</td>
                  <td>36</td>
                  <td>35</td>
                  <td>25</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="13">CytoQuest™ CR system</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Vimentin<sup>−</sup> CTCs</td>
                  <td>36</td>
                  <td>9</td>
                  <td>4</td>
                  <td>12</td>
                  <td>25</td>
                  <td>16</td>
                  <td>20</td>
                  <td>25</td>
                  <td>7</td>
                  <td>36</td>
                  <td>1</td>
                  <td>3</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Vimentin<sup>+</sup> CTCs</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>1</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>2</td>
                  <td>0</td>
                  <td>2</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td> Total</td>
                  <td>36</td>
                  <td>9</td>
                  <td>4</td>
                  <td>13</td>
                  <td>25</td>
                  <td>16</td>
                  <td>20</td>
                  <td>25</td>
                  <td>7</td>
                  <td>38</td>
                  <td>1</td>
                  <td>5</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </alternatives>
        </table-wrap>
      </sec>
    </sec>

    <sec sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Liver transplantation is used for the complete removal of tumor lesions, and the tumor recurrence and
        metastasis observed in HCC patients is likely related to CTCs. Therefore, the determination of CTCs by “liquid
        biopsies” is currently a major focus of investigation in monitoring patients with HCC undergoing LT.</p>
      <p>In the current study, we describe a platform that integrates microfluidic DLD arrays with a MACS separator and
        demonstrates its great potential for tumor antigen-independent CTC separation. At the optimal specimen flow rate
        of 60 μl/min and buffer flow rate of 100 μl/min, a CTC isolation efficiency ratio of 85.1 ± 3.2% and a high
        blood cell debulking efficiency (RBC, PLT, and WBC removal rates of 99.90% ± 0.03%, 99.95% ± 0.05%, and 98.50% ±
        0.13%, respectively) were achieved. In addition, there were no significant difference in the isolation
        performance of different tumor cell concentrations ranging from 50 to 8 × 10<sup>2</sup> cells/ml.</p>
      <p>Furthermore, the DLD device can provide continuous CTC separation. StraightFrom Whole Blood CD45 MicroBeads
        have the advantage of not requiring sample preparation for the rapid selection of CD45<sup>+</sup> cells
        directly from whole peripheral blood; thus, the cells produced from the DLD device can enter the MACS separator
        directly without centrifugation. Therefore, compared with other currently widely used methods for the negative
        selection of CTCs, such as RBC lysis or density gradient centrifugation, our capture platform has the advantage
        of simple operation.</p>
      <p>At the 3-month follow-up of the 12 HCC patients undergoing LT, CTCs were found in 12 (100%) patients. Ten of
        the 12 patients (83.3%) did not exhibit tumor metastasis or recurrence. Two of the 12 patients (16.7%) were
        diagnosed with metastasis, with recurrence in the lungs (<italic>n</italic> = 1) and bone (<italic>n</italic> =
        1).</p>
      <p>Compared with the Abnova CytoQuest™ CR system, our platform yielded similar results among patients with no
        metastasis, as determined by the Wilcoxon signed-rank test. However, examination of the two metastatic patients
        using the CytoQuest™ CR system before and LT revealed relatively fewer CTCs than examination by our platform.
      </p>
      <p>Our results suggest the identification of patients with tumor metastases and subpopulations of EMT-transformed
        CTCs. Previous studies have shown that CTCs undergo dynamic evolution under the strong selective pressure of
        chemotherapy, radiation therapy and any other therapeutic intervention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1">
          Aktipis et al., 2011</xref>). These CTCs have lower EpCAM expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-10">
          Giannelli et al., 2016</xref>) and increased metastatic potential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-19">Mani et
          al., 2008</xref>). Therefore, they are difficult to detect, isolate, and characterize using immunoaffinity
        enrichment strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-5">De Boer et al., 1999</xref>), and EpCAM<sup>low</sup>
        CTCs can be missed by the CytoQuest™ CR bulk sorting approach. In contrast, our antigen-independent platform
        maintained a high detection sensitivity while achieving higher CTC counts consistent with clinical observations.
        However, given that the sample size is relatively small, larger studies to confirm the present results are
        needed.</p>
      <p>We also observed limitations of the experiments. The DLD device uses a size-based particle separation approach,
        but tumor cells have different diameters. Although most CTCs are larger than RBCs, there are still a small
        number of CTCs that are similar in diameter to RBCs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-6">Fachin et al., 2017
        </xref>). These cells would not be separated by the device and would eventually be lost. In addition, although
        CTCs were highly enriched by our platform (HepG2-GFP cells had 852 × enrichment over RBCs, 57 × enrichment over
        WBCs, and 1,715 × enrichment over PLTs), the remaining cells still affect the CTC extraction purity. Finally,
        there is a delicate relationship between the flow rate and the separation efficiency. If researchers want to
        separate large volumes of blood samples at a high rate, cells under a high shear stress (<xref ref-type="bibr"
          rid="ref-18">Liu et al., 2013</xref>) can deform because of the high fluid velocities in our device, which may
        influence the cell isolation efficiency.</p>
      <p>In future studies, we will continue to improve the CTC extraction purity. In addition, using our platform, we
        will collect CTCs for further cell culture, drug screening, and molecular analyses.</p>
    </sec>

    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Here, we demonstrate the successful use of a platform that integrates a DLD structure with a MACS separator for
        isolating CTC isolation with high-efficiency regardless of surface epitopes. Compared with the CytoQuest™ CR
        system, which is based on an immunoaffinity method, our platform successfully identified a distinct
        subpopulation of EMT-transformed, vimentin<sup>+</sup> CTCs.</p>
      <p>However, the device still has several limitations, as described above. Our future studies will focus on
        continuing to improve the device.</p>
    </sec>

  </body>
  <back>

    <acknowledgement>
      <p>We thank American Journal Experts (AJE) for editing a draft of this manuscript.</p>
    </acknowledgement>

    <sec sec-type="additional-information">
      <title>Additional Information and Declarations</title>
      <fn-group content-type="competing-interests">
        <title>Competing Interests</title>
        <fn fn-type="conflict" id="conflict-1">
          <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>

      <fn-group content-type="author-contributions">
        <title>Author Contributions</title>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-1">
          <p>
            <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-1">Xuebin Wang</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed
            the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables.
          </p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-2">
          <p>
            <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-2">Liying Sun</xref> provided blood samples.
          </p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-3">
          <p>
            <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-3">Haiming Zhang</xref> provided blood samples.
          </p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-4">
          <p>
            <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-4">Lin Wei</xref> provided blood samples.
          </p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-5">
          <p>
            <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-5">Wei Qu</xref> provided blood samples.
          </p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-6">
          <p>
            <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-6">Zhigui Zeng</xref> provided blood samples.
          </p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-7">
          <p>
            <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-7">Ying Liu</xref> provided blood samples.
          </p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-8">
          <p>
            <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-8">Zhijun Zhu</xref> contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools,
            authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft, provided blood samples.
          </p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>

      <fn-group content-type="other">
        <title>Human Ethics</title>
        <fn id="addinfo-1">
          <p>The following information was supplied relating to ethical approvals (i.e., approving body and any
            reference numbers):</p>
          <p>Approval from the Beijing Friendship Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (code: 2018-P2-114-01) was
            obtained for the use of all samples using a protocol that conforms to the provisions of the Declaration of
            Helsinki.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>

      <fn-group content-type="other">
        <title>Data Availability</title>
        <fn id="addinfo-2">
          <p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p>
          <p>The raw data are available in the figures and tables in the article.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>

    </sec>

    <ref-list content-type="authoryear">

      <title>References</title>

      <ref id="ref-1">
        <label>Aktipis et al. (2011) Reference mentioned in the article text format- </label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aktipis</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kwan</surname>
              <given-names>VSY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>KA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neuberg</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maley</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jacobs</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Overlooking evolution: a systematic analysis of cancer relapse and therapeutic resistance
            research</article-title>
          <source>PLOS ONE - Journal name where reference is published</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <elocation-id>e26100 - article number of journal</elocation-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0026100</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>

    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
